# **Mathias Verraes**

mathias@verraes.net • Ghent, Belgium • Born 1979-07-02

# **Objective**

I am looking for a PHP Lead or Architect position, or freelance opportunities, where I can apply and expand my skills in analysis and software design.

# Summary

Technical Lead and Senior Software Engineer, with 6 years of experience, specializing in object-oriented analysis, design, and programming (OOAD, OOP) and Resource Oriented Architecture (REST). Expert PHP developer, among others with the Zend and Symfony2 frameworks. Background in Document and Content Management Systems, E-commerce and online fundraising. Focus on agile methodologies, Domain-Driven Design (DDD), and refactoring. Emphasis on Quality Assurance, using Test-Driven Development (TDD) and continuous integration. Enjoys mentoring and motivating team members.

## **Skills**

Languages	PHP, SQL, Javascript
Frameworks	Zend, Symfony2, Doctrine2
Databases	MySQL, Oracle 11g, Lucene, (MongoDB)
Development tools	Git, Subversion, Eclipse
Quality Assurance	PHPUnit, Hudson/Jenkins, JIRA
Deployment tools	Ant, Phing
Documentation	UML, Sphinx
Operating systems	Linux, OS X, Windows
Human languages	Dutch (native), English (fluent speaking and writing), French (basic)

## **Education**

Master in Music, Royal Conservatory - Ghent, Belgium - 1998-2003 I am an autodidact in the field of software development.

# **Work Experience**

#### Marlon - Ghent, Belgium - April 2011 - present

Senior Architect

SMS-Parking 4411.be (Mobile-for / Belgacom)

- proposed and implemented steps for refactoring a large legacy codebase (250 kLoC)
- built tools for a specialized security analysis
- performed ongoing maintenance and improved test coverage

#### Webshop project

- Designed and built a DDD architecture for a reusable Webshop core
- Led a team of four from start to deployment

## Delius - Ghent, Belgium - July 2010 - March 2011

Freelance Consultant

- Designed and built a centralized REST service for online fundraising applications
- Led a team of three in building clients applications for the framework
- Introduced TDD and Pair Programming into the team

## Timble - Diest, Belgium - July 2007 - June 2010

Senior Architect

- Envisioned and built Nooku Framework, a new RAD core to replace the Joomla framework
- Built Nooku Content, an application for managing multilingual content
- Turned Joomlatools DOCman, a dying open source DMS, into a successful commercial GPL application
- Consulted for clients such as the Belgian Police, the Italian Institute of Technology, the British National Health Service

#### Freelance Consultant - September 2005 - July 2007

• Built and deployed custom CMS solutions, based around Joomla

# Freelance music composer - 2002 - 2008

- Wrote music for short films and documentaries, TV commercials and pop albums
- Founded and conducted an a cappella pop choir, wrote arrangements

# **Community Engagement**

I am an open source enthusiast and have contributed to many OSS projects. As a speaker, I have been invited to talk about technical topics at many Joomla conferences all over Western Europe. When time permits, I maintain a blog on software development.

## **Hobbies and interests**

I enjoy reading both fiction and non-fiction; my current interests are Systems Thinking, and Evolutionary Biology. I founded a food degustation club and organize tastings.

Mathias Verraes • mathias@verraes.net • Ghent, Belgium • Last updated August 30, 2011